FRANCISCO LÓPEZ-SANCHO

SENIOR DEVELOPER

Specialized in Java and Scala

franciscolopezsancho@gmail.com Tel. 07918187043

Profile

I really love coding, obssessed with its elegance but in the scope of delivering.

I consider very important to be part of a team and tend to empathize very easily.

Question everything. Myself included if not first, can't help it.

And almost always I'm pushing to improve. Not a big fun of resting.

Skills

Development

Testing

Architecture & design

9 years developing software, currently backend using Scala and Java TDD and BDD evangelist

Ample experience in designing and developing solutions from end to end. From requirement gathering to deployment.

Technical Knowledge

Development

Elastic Transcoder, SQS,

IT Ops Chef,Puppet

Core Java

RDS, OpsWork,

Miscelánea

Scala, Akka, Spray Spring, JPA, JSF EMR,Datapipeline

Misceranea

Junit, Mockito, ScalaTest

Js: Backbone,Angular,Knockout

Selenium,Jmeter Hudson,Sonar

SOA, Web Services

Subversion, Git
Virtualization

Mayon Artifactory

Ruby on Rails

VMWare, Virtual Box, Vagrant

Maven,Artifactory Scripting in Linux

Elasticsearch, Kibana, Logstash

Databases

Apache Tomcat, Weblogic, Jetty

Spark

Oracle, MySql, MongoDB

VBA Joomla

R, Python (Around ML)

AWS: EC2,EB,S3,Glacier,

UNIX (Linux, AIX, OSX)

Experience

Senior Java/Scala Software Engineer Cognia

07/2015-today

I've done a couple of projects by now. As first contact with the platform, I created (picked Cucumber) a new layer of BDD tests around an existing public HTTP API. After that, designed and implemented a fault-tolerance audit system. Choosing Scala, Spark (deployed in Amazon EMR) and Amazon Datapipeline to fullfil the requirements. The solution is stable now. Lately involved in API throttling, design and implementation, and helping QA guys to learn how to automate more of the testing in many different areas. All mentioned technologies have been introduced by me into the company.

Tools used Eclipse, SequelPro, Maven, Jenkins, Command Line, Amazon Web Services

Senior Java/Scala Software Engineer IFPI

12/2013-07/2015

I developed multiple solutions to help legal music commerce all around the world. Processing Data, building APIs as REST Web Services are some of the projects developed, some others involve Machine Learning and some Data Analisis with R. Almost every single solution works in a High Performance environment, 24/7. There's been many small projects in the last year and some quite big. One of those big projects processes social interactions (Twitter,Facebook,Tumblr...) in order to find whether they had ilegal content. It was the signature project in 2014 and I did most of it, from backend to frontend. Develop is based on Java, Scala, Akka, Spring, JPA through Test Driven Development. This tools query SQL and NoSQL Databases, MongoDB to be exact

The core team is eight people. I'm in charge of introducing new technologies to the rest of the group and give support to two juniors

Tools used Eclipse, SqlDeveloper, Maven, Hudson, Command Line, Amazon Web Services

Senior Java Software Developer

02/2012-11/2013

Argonet Comunicaciones S.L.

This project was an internal web solution for the Ministry of Defence. It was a Web application that allowed CRUD of complex tasks and also of its single elements.

Develop is based on JSF2, Spring, JPA and SOAP web services through Test Driven Development. Responsible for implementing migration from a legacy technology to Java, frontend and backend. In a team of four deciding best practices around JSF2. In all area leading Testing Driven Development. Tools used Eclipse, SqlDeveloper, Maven, Hudson, Sonar.

Java Software Developer SoftwareAG Spain

09/2008-02/2012

Project 1 - 11/2010-02/2012

This project was a Web Application for savings banks to provide capital grant to associations in a national scope. Application aimed to manage the following features: capital solicitation, steps until acceptation and track of the status of the process.

Developed in a BPM, ESB and WS oriented framework.

Responsible for implementing required features, frontend and backend.

Tools used Eclipse, VmWare, SqlDeveloper, Ant.

Project 2 - 09/2008-11/2010

This project was a Web Application for savings banks in a national scope to manage personal loans and mortgages. Application aimed to manage the following features: loan or mortgages solicitation, steps until acceptation and track of the process itself.

Developed in a BPM, ESB and WS oriented framework.

Responsible for implementing required features, frontend and backend.

Tools used Eclipse, VmWare, SqlDeveloper, Ant.

Ruby Software Developer

06/2007-06/2008

Intec. New Technologies consulting

This project was a Web Application aimed to support Entrepreneurs in her business development under "Plan Avanza 2007" of Spanish Government. Application was designed as a table game. Each step would develop skills mostly through a little bit of theory and some question.

Developed using MySql, Ruby on Rails and an Apache Server.

Responsible for implementing required features, frontend and backend.

Tools used TextMate, MySqlWorkbench.

Microsoft Office Trainer

2000-2007

Different companies

Training Microsoft Office to different clients as NATO or Airbus

Other Projects (after 9 to 5 job)

Ruby Software Developer Intec Consultancy Solutions Ltd

03/2013-08/2013

This project was a Web application to manage videos, upload them and watch them, similar to youtube but the idea was to present different topics to open up discussions.

Develop is based on Backbone, Coffescript and Ruby on Rails.. Integration with Facebook, Twitter and Amazon Web Services and Nimbb.

Responsible for implementing migration from a Knockout technology to Backbone in the frontend and refactoring Backend to reduce it to a nutshell composed of API REST Services.

Tools used VirtuaBox, Vim, AWS EC2, S3 and OpsWork.

Education

ORACLE CERTIFIED PROFESSIONAL

Java SE 6 Programmer

UNED - Universidad Nacional de Educación a Distancia (2011-2014)

Philosophy Coursera

R programming, Reproducible Research, Statistical inference

Languages

Spanish Native level

English

High Level, written and spoken